# 大家好 今天去挖點那個五指毛桃來
Hi everyone! Today we're gonna pick some, well, some hairy figs (roots).
# 用來煲那個 雞湯
to make a, a chicken soup.
# 就在後山 後山這裡很多的
Right on our hill, on our hill, there are a lot.
# 拿這個小鋤頭子來
I'm going with this little pickax.
# 這裡上 危險啊
This way up. It's dangerous.
# 你看 這條路
Look! This path,
# 很久都沒來上山砍竹子啦
it has been a long time since my last time here for the bamboos.
# 這裡現在到處都長滿了野草
Now the weed is growing everywhere.
# 你看 這個就是五指毛桃啦 (註︰這個「就」字英文似乎沒有很好的翻譯，唯有寫得清楚一點)
Look! This is what we're looking for, hairy fig.
# 找了那麼遠 至少找了一兩公里才把它找上來
It's such a long way! We've been searching for at least a kilometre or two along the path before reaching it.
# 砍掉
Chop it down!
# 這個不要了
We don't need this part.
# 只要挖這個根
We only need to dig out the root,
# 就可以啦
and that's it.
# 你看 這個
Look! Here it is.
# 要把它的根挖出來
We gotta dig out the root.
# 這根才是
It's the root,
# 最主要的
which matters.
# 這個 太小啦 這個根
This one, is too small, this root.
# 你看
Look!
# 那麼小就被我挖回去啦
So I've dug it out though it's so small.
# 沒辦法 就找到你
I've no choice. You're the only one here.
# 這兩根
These two...
# 這裡還有一根
Here's one more.
# 那麼小
It's so small.
# 那麼小也是
But size doesn't matter.
# 你看 這個還是條老根
Look! This is an old root, in fact.
# 找到條老根 粗粗的
Got an old root, it's rather thick.
# 看到沒有
See?
# 這個就是
Here it is.
# 根拉不起來就不要啦
I leave it alone. I can't pull out the root.
# 就搞這根就行了
I'll have just this one.
# 這裡也有一棵哦 這裡
Here's one more, here.
# 你看
Look!
# 五指 五指毛桃
Hairy, hairy figs
# 這個好深啊 這個
It goes very deep, this one.
# 你看 終於拔起來啦
Look! I've dug it out finally.
# 它這個
This one...
# 它上面還有一棵 我看到
There's another one up there. I saw it.
# 你看
Look!
# 這是野生的黃花倒水蓮哦
This is wild "huang hua dau shui lian" (a type of herbal leaf).
# 我們土話叫
In our local dialect here, it's called,
# 鴨腳木
duck feet wood,
# 鴨腳
duck feet,
# 鴨腳樹 叫鴨腳樹還是
duck feet tree. Is it duck feet tree or?
# 它這個是用來 也 好像也可厶用來那個
This is used for, like, it seems that it can be, you know...
# 不知道用來幹嘛的 反正 老人家
No ideas what it's for. Anyway, the elderlies,
# 經常 經常說這個很珍貴
always, always say that it's rare.
# 先不要破壞它的 生態
Let's not destroy its, ecosystem.
# 讓它長高高
Instead we let it grow and grow well,
# 長高一點
and be a tall nice plant.
# 你看它的 小小黃花 像不像那個小鴨子
Have a look at its little, little yellow flowers? Do they look like the little duckies?
# 再去下 往下面去
Let's go down, down further,
# 看下有沒有
and see if there are any more.
# 這邊 上面都沒有了
Here are, no more up there.
# 你看 這還有一個 一指毛桃 (註︰這個有點麻煩，五指毛桃的五指是指葉上有五個指狀的葉冠，但這棵的葉只有一個，但這個「指」的概念沒有在英文名字中表達出來)
Look! This leaf has just one, one lobe.
# 就長了一個指 一個指出來的
It has just one, one lobe.
# 這個也可以用
This is also fine.
# 有五指的不夠 用一指的來湊
There are not enough five-lobe ones (the normal ones). This can fill the gap.
# 啊 這個
Ah! This is,
# 這一根還
this one is still...
# 就長了那麼一點
It's just a little bit here.
# 這一棵 腐爛的木頭 壓在這裡
This one, a rotten wood, is pressing on it.
# 這一棵
This one...
# 逃的脫 逃的脫我的掌心
You think you can escape, escape from my hand?
# 那麼小根 扯 扯起來
It's so small. I pull, pull it out.
# 差不多啦 看路邊上還有沒有
It's almost there. Let's see if there are any more on the sides of the path.
# 再挖幾個就夠啦
I just need a few more.
# 你看 這裡有一棵哦
Look! Here's one!
# 一定要用力挖 它這根好長啊 它這根
I gotta dig forcefully. Its root goes really deep, its root.
# 被我扯掉一棵下來
I've pulled off a piece.
# 你看 挖到啦
Look! Here it is!
# 就那一點點
It's just a tiny little bit here.
# 它一棵就一點點的 不是很多
There's never a lot, as each root is just a tiny little bit.
# 因為
Cuz,
# 不是種植的 種植的就很大棵
they're not cultivated. The cultivated ones are really big.
# 你看 差不多可以 煲一隻雞啦
Look! It's should be enough, enough for a chicken.
# 回去 洗一下 曬乾
Let's take it back, wash it and dry it under the sun.
# 明天就搞一隻雞來煲一下
I'll get a chicken and make a soup tomorrow.
# 你看 上次我們種的西瓜
Look! These are the watermelons that we planted last time.
# 好不容易結了一個起來哦
Finally, ultimately, we have one watermelon now.
# 你看這個西瓜 都長那麼大啦
Have a look at this watermelon. It's so big now.
# 下次來 等它熟了之後
I'll come again next time. When it's ripe,
# 我就把它摘來吃了
I'll pick it and finish it.
# 誰都不能摘啊
No one is allowed to pick it.
# 誰摘了我跟誰急
If anyone dares to pick it, I'll squabble with him, without any hesitation.
# 好不容易長了一個 全部都死完啦 就剩下這一棵樹
This is the last survivor. All others have died and only this one remains,
# 沒死的
and is still alive.
# 難得長一個瓜出來
It's an invaluable single watermelon.
# 每天都用那個有機肥
Everyday, I spray the, the organic fertiliser,
# 潑到那個 它根部
onto its, its root.
# 才能長出那麼好的
That's why it's growing so well.
# 要不然就長不了那麼好的
It wouldn't be growing so well otherwise.
# 這個就要洗一下 清洗一下
It needs to be washed, and cleansed.
# 差不多洗乾淨啦 洗乾淨還要曬一下的哦
It's almost done now. When it's cleaned, it needs to be dried under the sun, you know.
# 曬了才好吃
So it becomes much more tasty.
# 不曬就不夠香
The aroma is greatly reduced if it's not dried.
# 拿到這邊曬一下
I'll let it dry under the sun here.
# 要把這個曬一下 要曬乾來啦
It needs to be dried, dried under the sun first,
# 把裡面的水分 曬乾
to dry up all the moisture inside.
# 再用那個
And then we can,
# 大火去煲它 一煲湯的話 它就把裡面的香味釋放出來啦
cook it on high heat. Then in the soup, the aroma will be unlocked.
# 所以 如果想直接 直接煲也可以 那肯定沒那麼香的
So, it's alright if you wanna use it right, right away. But then the aroma is certainly affected.
# 來曬一下 曬乾來 明天去一隻雞來
Let's leave it here, dry it. We're gonna fetch a chicken tomorrow,
# 燉
and stew it!
# 你看 這個于指毛桃就已曬乾了哦
Look! The hairy figs (roots) are now dried.
# 就缺個雞啦 我去村裡面搞一個鴨子來
A chicken is what we need now. Let me go into the village, and get a duck.
# 哦 不是 搞一隻雞
Ah, no! Get a chicken
# 先放在這裡 我去搞隻雞來
Leave it here first. I'm gonna get a chicken.
# 我去上面那個村子 看一下 有沒有雞 搞一隻來
I'm going to the village up there and see, if there are any chicken. I'll get one there.
# 沒抓到
Missed
# 搞了一隻
So here's one.
# 好像這個有蛋的 我換一隻來 不要這個
It seems that it has eggs. I'm not taking it. I'll take another one.
# 我一下它有沒有蛋
Let me feel if it has any eggs.
# 這個沒蛋 就這個
No eggs. Then this one
# 你看 這固公雞 它是以前廠裡面拿上來的哦
Look! This rooster, it was taken here from our site, you know.
# 要不然都被那個小黑咬 咬死啦
Otherwise Blacky would have bitten, bitten it to death.
# 活的最久的一隻
This rooster has the longest live.
# 不叫的 它現在都是
It doesn't yelp. It's now,
# 一身都是 紅毛 紅光發亮
covered with red feather, shiny red feather.
# 說明它的日子過得很不錯哦
It's an evidence of its joyful days here.
# 以前都很瘦的 在都那麼胖
It used to be very skinny, but it's so big now.
# 不叫了它
It's not yelping now.
# 你看 那麼肥啦它
Look! It's so big now.
# 你看 這個魚塘 在有草魚啦 放了 幾十條草魚下去
Look! In this pond, there are grass carps now. We've put dozens of grass carps into the pond.
# 到時候就可以去撈啦
We can catch them later.
# 還有其他魚的 還有鯽休放了好多下去
There are also other fish, We've put a lot of "ji yu" (local carps) too.
# 每天割點草給它吃
We feed them with grass every day.
# 長得很快的
They grow really fast.
# 好啦 先回去啦
Alright! Let go back first.
# 來來來來來 有骨頭吃啦
Come here, come here, come here! I have bones for you.
# 骨頭你們都不要
Are you sure that you don't want bones?
# 我燒點開水
Let me boil some water.
# 你看 這個雞 雪白雪白的
Look! This chicken, is snowy white.
# 很靚吧
Beautiful, isn't it?
# 這一個小雞腿
Here's a tiny chicken leg.
# 打火機都不見啦
The lighter is gone.
# 很快 很快就著了
It glows, it glows in no time.
# 我先燒點開水 這開水燒燙來再放雞肉
Let me boil some water first. I'll put the chicken when the water boils.
# 兄弟 兄弟的打氣筒
My buddy's, my buddy's air pump.
# 用來這個 吹這個 這麼猛
I blow it, blow it here. It's so strong.
# 很好用的哦 從這邊吹
It's pretty nice. I blow on this side.
# 誒呦 反過來吹
Ayo! Wrong side
# 剛好拿腳趾 腳趾插進去
It just fits, fits my toe here.
# 火旺啦這樣 你看 那邊 誒呀
The fire is getting strong here, look, on that side. Aya!
# 沒燒掉 可 可以啦
It's not burnt. Al, alright now!
# 放點生薑下去 生薑可以這樣
I put some ginger. The ginger can be, like,
# 兩個生薑這樣一捏就可以
crush the two gingers together. Done!
# 就碎掉啦 你看
So it's smashed. Look!
# 這個碎了
It's smashed.
# 這個捏不碎
I couldn't smash it.
# 哎 可以啦
Ay! It's alright now!
# 生薑放下去接下來就是雞肉
When the ginger is there, next, the chicken.
# 這雞肉也放下去
I put the chicken as well.
# 水下夠
Not enough water
# 再加點山泉水
Let me add some spring water.
# 把這個五指毛桃也放下去
I now put the hairy fig into the wok,
# 全部一起放下去
put them all into the wok.
# 就這樣大火燒它 一直燒
So here it is. Keep it cooking, on high heat.
# 一直燒
Keep it cooking,
# 燒到它沒火為止
until the fire goes off.
# 來 慢慢燒
Alright! Leave it cooking,
# 煮一個小時
for an hour.
# 就夠啦 它這老母雞來的
And that's it. This is an old hen.
# 你看 這個知了哦
Look! This is a cicada.
# 它飛到我身上來的
It lands on me.
# 都不知道怎麼回事你看
Who knows what happened. Look!
# 可能想
I think it may want to,
# 想跟大家見個面
want to say hi to everyone.
# 它 震動 震動那麼厲害
It's shaking, shaking so forcefully.
# 還動
It's still moving.
# 動不了哦
Now it stops.
# 還小的時候我們經常抓來玩
We always played with these bugs when we were small.
# 這樣一捏它就會
Here, if you squeeze it, it will...
# 它是從這個發聲的 它這裡有個聲帶
The sound is coming from here. Here's a vocal cord.
# 我一捏它帶 誒
If I squeeze its vocal cord...ay!
# 你看 啞了吧
Look! It's now dumb, isn't it?
# 就在這裡
It's right here.
# 它還小的時候是可以吃的 那個知了
It's edible when it was small, the cicada.
# 特別好吃
It's really tasty.
# 現在都老了
But it's old now.
# 我又不吃你
I'm not eating you.
# 不好吃
You're not tasty.
# 老了又不能吃了
The old ones are not edible.
# 現在你自由啦
You're free now.
# 飛吧
Fly!
# 不走是不是
You're not leaving, are you?
# 你看 我跟它有感情了
Look! We have developed boding.
# 看見沒有
See?
# 是不是 它知道感恩
Is it, because it is grateful?
# 是我救了它哦
After all, I've saved its life.
# 誒呦 跑啦
Eyo? It runs away.
# 可以 放點鹽
Alright! Put some salt.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 你看
Look!
# 這白色的湯馬上就出來啦
The milky white soup is here immediately.
# 蓋好來
Cover it up,
# 繼續煲
and keep it cooking.
# 來 給你好吃的哦
Hey! I have some good food for you.
# 它不怎麼吃 吃一點點
It's not really eating. It eats just a tiny little bit.
# 哇 熟啦熟啦熟啦熟啦
Wa! It's done, it's done, done, done!
# 冒那麼大的煙
It's so smoky.
# 嘗一下
Let me have a try.
# 嗯 好吃
Um! Tasty!
# 老母雞哦 現在都燉爛啦
It's an old hen. And it's now soft and mushy.
# 可以可以可以 開鍋啦
Not bad, not bad. Let's get started!
# 嗯
Um!
# 拿個碗來
Let me take a bowl.
# 哇 好久 沒吃過這個雞肉啦
Wa! I haven't had chicken for a long time.
# 這個是老母雞
This is an old hen.
# 老母雞燉這個
Old hen boiled with, you know,
# 五指毛桃
hairy fig.
# 好香
It smells great.
# 燉了兩小時 母雞都燉熟啦
We've boiled it for two hours. And the hen is thoroughly cooked now.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡吧
Alright! The video ends here.
# 你看這些小狗 全部都看著我
These doggies, are all looking at me.